[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I was saying before, in terms of the sense of self, the way to undo it is incorrectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you become established in the practice of mindfulness, of the experience as a whole, as you said, which sort of reveals this sense of self as kind of separate from it,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you get established in that sort of practice, knowing that you're not supposed to, well, that it's actually impossible to to bring that background sense of self, that ambiguous sense of self, to bring it forward, to bring it in front of you, to see it, because then something else will be very unclear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you kind of give up these futile attempts, based on these wrong habits of expecting to get it in front of you, expecting to grasp it, then, eh... that sense of self can become the optional manifest in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you said something correctly, that background sense of self, background sense of I am, because it is in a way more general than everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that once you have discerned the principle that it's actually fully determined by whatever you have put in front of you, in that experience as a whole, that fully depends upon it, that it's inconceivable without.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same like dependence on nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, just enough to have the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to then... in the beginning you have to, but then you don't need to have to look for these determinations, even along the right lines.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, by then, it becomes apparent that whatever has a reason, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you start seeing impermanence in simple thing... in simple fact that things have manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how ambiguous, how much we're back down, how much... it's impossible to... to kind of grasp them, hold them closely, and spread them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it's appeared in any shape or form, distant, ambiguous, remote, whatever, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it has begun.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it has a beginning, by necessity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Implies the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, ending is the instant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the meaning of beginning?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: That it wasn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: That could... one of its meanings could be...
[SPEAKER_00]: I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what does it reveal, basically?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it reveal?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It reveals that it wasn't before, because... And if it wasn't before, it cannot be an internal self.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were an internal self, it would have been there all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels... the internal self feels... You can't... like, so bad, you can't remember how it feels.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That whole everlasting is a concept that can be undone in this presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I told you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to... You're not supposed to get rid of that sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just supposed to undermine its gratuitous notion of permanence, of being constant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have the experience as a whole and then you have that background sense of self that people can mystify or
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, whatever, deny, mystify, call it observer, or aware, pure awareness, pristine awareness, or whatever new-age terms you might come up with, the fact is, there is that thing, there is a background, that you cannot have in the front, that there is the observer of the observed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that you still assume, imply, permanence associated with that observer.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how far you mystify it, what word you use, the fact that you
[SPEAKER_01]: Regarding, it has a notion of mind to it, more real, more controlled, more of a sensitive experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not interfering with that, whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you want to interfere with, is that gratuitous notion of permanence associated with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how you interfere with that, the only way you can do it, is indirectly, by seeing it inseparable from that which is permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, which is impermanent, which is fully understood as something that will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you then, through the, like, literally fabrication, through your efforts, you kind of establish, you force upon the dependence of that observer, inverted commas, quote-unquote observer, if you just, like, force the dependence upon that which is observed, that dependence will become revealed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is genuine dependence of the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: And through emulating it, first simply based on the external advice, through emulating that dependence, then it will become apparent eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it becomes apparent only after sufficient number of time, after it's been repeated a number of times, basically, as long as it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: For some people it takes more, for some people it takes less.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you've been repeating this principle that you adopted on faith externally, as a true principle, whereby observer is determined by that which is being observed, it's inseparable from it, it cannot be conceived apart from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you keep emulating that, because that is the actual nature of things, then it will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like... it's complete... like complete darkness in the beginning and somebody just tells you to keep repeating these steps, they will eventually bring the light, but initially you don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the point of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you see that certain things, external things, are not in your control, like your body, the weather, or the bus getting outside, or people liking you, your reputation is not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, if you truly see that your reputation is not in control, if you find out that people are speaking bad about you,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're not necessarily going to get upset.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you knew, you thoroughly contemplated that this is out of my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they could say good things, they could say bad things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when they say bad things... You know, the family of the mind has withdrawn from that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're not... when you realize that you're...
[SPEAKER_01]: The very sense of self is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind has withdrawn from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what about, like, the view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Your attitude towards things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, again, your attitude towards things, which is dependent on things being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Other things, I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you go beyond that view as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude is beyond your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's the other hand.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, the Noble Eightfold Path, in the case of another hand, like, they added another, which is basically beyond... What was the...?
[SPEAKER_01]: It was going beyond the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right intention, right effort, it goes on, on, on, on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, basically, like, beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did it go that swiftly, the last two?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was it the ten factors, ten... Well, I can't remember exactly, but basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: The global path becomes ten.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was basically, like, what was clearly indicated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Ārya-sāvaka, of any form, still has a degree of a view, and for another hunt, he fully overcomes even the views as well, so he goes beyond the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what ārya-saṅkhya is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the view is, like, you can see very much as a law, as an eternal law, as an impersonal law, as a law that doesn't subject to anything, kind of, on the physical world, but actually, it's inseparable from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In its phenomenological nature, it will not be there if things have not arisen beforehand, on account of which you have developed a view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, that view might seem independent of it, but the fact is, if the matter in its entirety disappears, you can't remain holding the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Given the wide, wide view...
[SPEAKER_01]: The wide and broad view, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you go beyond the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you see, like, you're fully abandoning and that's how to develop the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The person can't go beyond... you can't see that your choice or the choosing is not you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, going beyond the view doesn't mean finding some area beyond the view which you then inhabit.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, going beyond the view means abandoning the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abandoning depends on the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you said...
[SPEAKER_01]: But the view should be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but then it ceases to be the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: The direction is still there, but it ceases to be the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: The view is for as long as you are taking it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same thing as you just said.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you contemplate that praise is out of your control, and you truly abandon it, then the blame will not affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you contemplate the view, views are fully arisen based on the arisen things beforehand, then you fully abandon that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that doesn't mean they never appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means they'll never ever be yours, which means they'll never be manifested as views, because using the word view implies my point of view, my direction, my take on things, or whatever, how certain it may be.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is to go beyond it, which means the mind is not established upon it either, well, further, in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, going beyond the view does not mean going into the realm of transcendental existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means mind letting go of the view as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But truly letting go of the view, not kind of all let go of the views now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like fully developing this principle of simultaneous dependence that I've been talking about, to the full extent whereby even the subtlety of views is renounced as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: As like a center of my everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just completely disarmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that comes with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about figuring out what's beyond the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about figuring out what's behind this observer, or where he comes from, or what he is, or what can I pin it to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all about seeing that no matter what it is as a background, it will depend on the foreground.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, it depends on the foreground, right there, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it depends not in a linear sense, whereby one led to the number two,
[SPEAKER_01]: But more like in the simultaneous sense, where one determines one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the presence of it is inseparable from this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you hold... and as I said, it can be as general as mind and body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to necessarily pursue any more particular definitions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind and body, physical and mental, you can call it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, mental, you have to make this connection, you have to discern it, and then keep repeating them until they become apparent, whereby you see that mind, no matter how independent it might seem, how mind might feel, it's inseparable from the presence of the physical body, like inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can imagine physical body dying, but the mind continuing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's like not falling from phenomenology.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means that's not mindful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're mindful, you will see whenever there is a thought of you as a whatever personality or mind or whatever, there are implied images of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: of your matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or something, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a space.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like an eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, that is matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That stands for what matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I cannot even conceive anything mental without this matter already being there, given beforehand, simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the other way around as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that absolutely no matter how far out into the matter you go, you realize this matter is equally inconceivable if I... if I'm not determining it, if I'm not designating it, even mutually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, recognizing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And designation, recognition, everything, that's all mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: That all pertains to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, well, no matter... like, I can truly examine the deformities.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I'm examining is the perception of that matter, which is matter, can never be directly accessed in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your body cannot be accessed directly in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's that because of which your mind is there in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, if you look at, like, if you...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's the same, like, if you look at choosing... because choosing is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If we don't get any further than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look at choosing, and then... you couldn't choose anything if there wasn't these choices there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even though you've got the power, and you've got the power to choose between good and bad, I wouldn't...
[SPEAKER_01]: Both are already there beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: The choice is given beforehand, which means the power of choice is fully determined upon the things that are given beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, free will is the same, I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you said it's free will, but
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a freedom to choose this or that, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fully within the given parameters of choice, which means it's fully imprisoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not free-free, because you can't create anything free.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can only shift from left to right, or whatever, within that which is already given.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you cannot even conceive stepping outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because stepping outside of it, usually people assume is, I refrain from choice, thus I don't engage in it, and that was another choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Refraining from choosing is something you just chose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, why do you choose something over another?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: See, that's your assumption, that they would want to explain the choice, which means you want to take the control over the choice, which means it would want to put a center in your choice, which means it's taken as yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes from the assumption of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you choose something over the other?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I mean, okay, I would... but what about, like, being... like, there's... there's tendencies in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's underlying tendencies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you said... couldn't you say there was a reason for... Well, the thing is, see, it's the choice works in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the other day, when we spoke, when I referred to that simile from the suttas of
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the rain falls on the top of the mountain, the little springs from the top of the mountain, but then, as they're coming down, they're getting bigger and bigger, because they're collecting more and more water.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have the pools, mountain pools, filled with water.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, they start overflowing, they fill up the lower pools, and lower... and then, you have the ocean, but it all comes from the same water.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you're asking now is already on the level of ocean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already on the level of full development, and then you're, what did I choose?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, basically, all of your choices that you're
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they're all formal directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Choice is a direction you choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, every particular direction has been determined by more general directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say, well, why did I choose this right here?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I choose this thing right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, there's always going to be an element of, kind of, spontaneity.
[SPEAKER_01]: To a degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes more, sometimes less, depending how much people...
[SPEAKER_01]: But spontaneity is a valid phenomenon, a circumstance, a chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a phenomenon that you can then choose to be the reason for your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But more important than that, why you choose particular things is because of the stuff you chose in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now people, for example, like, you know, there are many cases that I met of people who get inspired with Buddha's teaching, want to practice Buddha's teaching, but they've been out in the lay world for quite some time, accumulated things, accumulated people, accumulated family and children, and now they can't just choose to leave it all behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then they say, well, obviously, it's not my fault that I can't go and become a monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, actually, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to see it as a fault, it is a fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of the 30 years beforehand,
[SPEAKER_01]: You've been choosing all the things they've been taking away elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you did not consider at the time, when you wanted to find a wife and have children, that, who knows, in my 10 years I might despise it all.
[SPEAKER_01]: In 15 years I might want to leave and become a monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't think that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just thought what your sense desire was dictating you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So often, people's choices are determined by senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because senses are independent five animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just drag you left and right, and then you think you... Well, you are choosing left or right in terms of the beautiful sights, because you've already given in to the pressure of beautiful sights, beautiful touches, agreeable tastings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's most often why people choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they just take for granted the criteria of sense pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start contemplating that, the danger in sense... you stop choosing the sense pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you stop choosing the sense pleasure, those pools will dry up, bit by bit by bit, and then they won't be fueled anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so there is the... there is the choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to find out, why did I choose to write this right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did I choose that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, start looking back.
[SPEAKER_01]: What did you choose beforehand and beforehand?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, I mean, more general.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean in a linear sequence, what I've chosen five minutes ago and 15 minutes ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean,
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did I choose... what did I choose to do with my life that led me to this point?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you say, why did I... why did I choose to go and live on top of a mountain now, when I could have gone to... well, because at first I've chosen to become a monk, ten, eleven years ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I've chosen to come to Sri Lanka.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I've chosen to find a more secluded place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, I have this particular choice that results out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, no matter how
[SPEAKER_01]: Spontaneous, the choice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are responsible for it, because of the previous choices you made, because of the previous choices you made, because of the previous choices you made.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of the choices you made, the options, so to speak, were given to you before and initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do choose a direction, and within that direction, you choose other directions, another direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, circumstance, accident, things happen, but that's all part of the human realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that just shows you that no matter how volitional your choices are, they're always going to remain, well, out of your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because no matter what you chose, what you built, what direction you took, it can all be taken away in one stroke of bad luck.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not like it's in someone else's control.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or something else's control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's when you project your sense of self that you can't let go of externally, and then you end up assuming a god, a god, and then you pray, and then you become super.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or a devil.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, then you tap into the kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Naturally inclined superstitiousness of people, which is basically praying to something external, because you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize that no matter how much effort you put, how far you go, how careful you choose, everything can be taken away the next second from you and destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you do, because you don't know that you're supposed to let go of your own sense of self, you don't see that as the way out, you can't even conceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yourself not being yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you just end up projecting that sense of self externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you end up worshipping trees, aes, stones, deities, whatever, externally, through that sense of self, as if...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize this is not in my control, but you, by default, assume that it's in someone else's control, or something else's control, which is still taking a self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Making assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you become superstitious.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't believe in anything, you become, like, magical.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think, oh, if I step on my left foot first, it's going to be a bad luck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still projected in the same external principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... if I look back to why... if I really ask myself, why am I choosing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I look back in general, as I said the other day, it was like, well, you would choose... you choose what is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You choose what you think is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it'll come down, like, right to the to the core, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You choose based on how you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you say, most often, you're, uh, you're craving for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The delight in pleasure is the reason, well, for doing many of the things you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the reason for choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because choice is one of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the reason why you choose certain choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the nature of choice remains regardless of the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Choice is one of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: The intentions, cetanā, that's already choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything is intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is directional in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just what intention you attend.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then your choice becomes down to attending to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha would often say, he carefully attends, not careless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you carelessly attend, then you already start fueling a certain directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by the time the choices are kind of crystallized as options, you're actually fully responsible, because you've been dwelling on those things in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if while somebody carelessly attends to the sign of beauty and ends up lusting after it,
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't be surprised that then his choice is about pursuing the central pleasure, or, okay, saying no to it, but there's nothing in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't say anything in between, because it's all about sensuality, because his mind's been burning.
[SPEAKER_01]: And obviously, then he'll choose to pursue it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not strong enough to say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: The choice of no is present in everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when you realize that you can, you yourself, can undermine everything as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this thing, there's
[SPEAKER_00]: That knowledge has to be presented to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know beforehand, yeah, in order to learn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there's a different way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, I didn't know there was a choice there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your intentions, your intentions become fueled by the simple attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what you attend more.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you attend at expense of what.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, those intentions then, determined further down the line, cause the forms of choices you made in your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to know that, if you just then, no matter what choices you made, if you still... like the example I gave, the man who wants to leave it all behind, but feels responsible for his family and he can't give it in, if he still doesn't give in to bad faith, and if he still doesn't obscure the sense of guilt that he himself brought himself into that position, if he starts to attend constantly on the freedom from suffering, on the Buddha's teaching or whatever, sooner or later,
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually, maybe not soon, but eventually, he will build enough resolve to leave it all behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just might take longer than somebody who doesn't have a family and kids and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they don't attempt it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to do it right now, but I can't do it because of my family.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they disown responsibility for it as if it wasn't them who built that family.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they don't think about it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they just cement, cement it, like, cement over it, as if it's done, it's sorted.
[SPEAKER_01]: I cannot possibly do it because of this, and I'm not responsible for it anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I'll just have to do what I can, with what I got.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll see that the choice to leave the world behind, or freedom, the choice to be free from suffering, the guy who's just living his life, whatever, having a family, whatever, you know, that choice,
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but what I'm talking about is, like, why would you... why would he choose that, or why he wouldn't choose that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why he wouldn't be able to choose, which is what you asked originally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because he's either too weak in regard to it, to such choice, too weak to say the... too weak to stir himself up, too weak to accept the pain that would come with it initially,
[SPEAKER_01]: Too weak to see through the immediate pleasure that appears as not fully gratifying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, it's pleasant to be in the safety of your home and family, but in the long run, it's more dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he's too weak to see any of that, because he's not attending to it on a daily basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, if he was to not give in to that kind of cover-up of his own guilt for his own choices, cover-up of his own responsibility for his own choices, he would be able to keep dwelling on it, to attend to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if he does attend sufficiently, there won't be no amount of children or family to keep you in their life, if you recognize the true danger of human existence, the peril of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you know, in the surface, there were people who just saw through it, who were, like, about to become kings or queens, with everything laid out for them, like, what everybody would just wish for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they were, like, disgusted with the whole thing and left it the next moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you say, why can't I leave it next moment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, whenever you leave it, it's going to be left the next moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how leaving works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why you can't reach to the next moment, where you leave things, is because you haven't been building it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you build it up through simply attending to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yoniso manasikāra, the proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the root of everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't know about those things you need to be attending to without... Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without a good friend to help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without somebody telling you what you need to attend to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that good friend is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it might be out of it, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a degree of just complete, like, circumstance.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at the same time, as I said, circumstances...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you might have been lucky to come across the Buddha's teaching, but luck has nothing to do with you choosing to practice or not, with you drilling and year after year making efforts of, like, undoing the ignorant habits of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's absolutely no room for luck there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, yeah, sometimes in the sutras, the monks who have developed the Sāghi powers to see beyond, they will say, oh, yeah, I met that person because in the previous life we were close and then we were bound to kind of revolve around each other no matter where we were reborn and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all that is irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: How it came to be, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're responsible for what you do on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for what you choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the thing is, see, many people, even back in the Buddhas, they came across the Buddha, but not all of them seen his wisdom, and not, like, not even half of them chose to follow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people can come across the purest of the dhamma instructions, and not even recognize it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they don't have that proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the two factors for the right view, proper attention in the absence of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: And proper attention, basically,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a moment that you go, ah, I can't do it rightly the right second.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Proper attention is an attitude of looking at things rightly, not obscuring the things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a responsible authentic attitude will be an attitude of proper attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, if nothing is instructed to you to properly attend, that proper attention in itself cannot lead you out of the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with the right attitude, the proper attitude, the attitude of proper attention, and the right instruction, you will know what to look for, you will know what to keep attending.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as we spoke before, it can't... enlightenment can't happen by luck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, attending to something rightly,
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be done way more than once.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be done countless numbers of times until that handle of ignorance, of the axe of ignorance, wears thin and thinner and thinner and thinner.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you pick up the axe once, the wooden handle, there's absolutely no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you don't know that you're supposed to keep doing it on and on and on and on and on and on for seven days, seven months, seven years, who knows, seven lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know that, there is nothing to indicate to you that you should pick that axe again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, you can pick it once, twice, five times, by accident, by chance, by your own reasoning.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there won't be any apparent proof or a verification that this is the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not anytime soon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, unless somebody tells you that that is the way of suffering and you keep sticking to it, you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like throwing a coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can throw a coin and you can get head five times, ten times, but it's simply impossible that thousand times, thousand throws will always yield the same result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doing this thousand times, without knowing that you're supposed to, it's not about head or tail, it's about actually throwing the coin, that's what undoes it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless somebody tells you that, you won't know, because it won't be apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why we, like, you know, some, somebody who did enlighten himself with his own efforts, without any external advice, is like the greatest, and through that simple trial and error, they took him, like, lifetimes to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, unless somebody tells you what you're doing now, keep doing it, maybe fine-tune it, or point out more, or whatever, inspiring similar ways to develop the same principle, unless you read it somewhere, unless you have faith in what you read, it's simply impossible that you'll repeat it exactly the same way for thousands of times, because there is no result to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no apparent result to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see the axe handle wearing clean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just can't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There might be someone who might want to ask, like, what can I have that will help me make the right choice all the time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What can I add?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is necessary for making the right choice all the time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can know that you made the right choice only after you have repeated it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, only after you discover you handled one thing, you'll know I wore a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_01]: People think it's like throwing the coin and then you throw it and you got it right.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter whether it's head or tail.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is thousands and thousands and thousands of times of flicking and flicking and flicking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize it wasn't about the head or tail, it was about wearing the dang coin down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And wearing of the coin is irrelevant to the result that you get when you throw the coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your expectations that lead you to results.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the actual effort of throwing it, regardless of the result, is what wore it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on another level, on another level of a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, just a similar word further, just one more thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, unless you know what you're supposed to do, through an affluence of another, be it reading, or suttas, or study, or whatever else, whatever way you might have arrived at it, it's impossible that you would have been repeating the same efforts in the same way
[SPEAKER_01]: for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no guidance on what those efforts are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just using your own judgment, and then your own judgment is influenced by the inevitable expectation of pleasure in the form of peace or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But basically, you would be acting out of your pleasure, which means there would be some craving, which means, unless somebody tells you externally, and then you have faith into that more than in what your own, like, initial inclinations, eh... you will not do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, you need to keep repeating that which is contrary to your own existence, going against the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since somebody... somebody defines the grain, so you can go against, you won't be able to go, because everything you do is with your grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need an external input in which you'll have faith to keep sticking to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But without that... without that external instruction, it's impossible that you would be repeating the same effort, the same quality of effort, sufficient amount of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person can attend to the right view accidentally, and then they can do it again and again.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they never heard about the right view, if they never heard what the right view is, if they never heard what to develop right view, how to develop right view, if they never heard what to look for in the right view,
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll never recognize that what they've just done was the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's unthinkable that they'll repeat the same experience thousands and thousands and thousands of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's simply unthinkable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they don't recognize that experience for what it is, so they won't know what to look for on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they might accidentally do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's impossible to become even a sotāpanna by sheer accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or by... Oh, I heard it once.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people hear something once, like in the suttas, they think, yeah, they understood it once because their minds were already developed through these right habits beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the same repetition has been already developed and now they go like the last kind of drip that sort of covered it already.
[SPEAKER_01]: But except that, you can't, you know, it comes down... it all comes down to the efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if someone is riddled with lust at one point, at one time, riddled with anger, they want to know how can I simply not choose that direction, to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I see that, I don't act.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can either continue with this lustful mode or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: What stops me from...?
[SPEAKER_00]: What makes me choose not to follow that lustful direction?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what makes me choose to go follow the lustful?
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if it comes to the point of being real, being right, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what you need to recognize is that you kind of let yourself get into that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once you're in that state, there is nothing else that you can do except endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is a form of choosing no.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, you know, the strength of mind to just withstand no is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that does not necessarily bring...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's necessary when things kind of come up of such nature that you just have to endure them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, basically, that's only, like, one way of dealing with it at a time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, fundamentally, you want to find a state where those things don't bother you at all, and there is no form of endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that comes with wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that wisdom comes with foreseeing these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you ended up in a state of rag... rag by anger or by loss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, for days and weeks before, you didn't pay any attention to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you paid attention to it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you were attending, or you were entertaining certain sensual notions, or certain irritable notions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you know, paired with a few circumstances, with something that happened, with a bad mood, with this, with a lack of sleep, now results in this full-on anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but what do I do right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what you do right here, right now, I recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right here, right now, was influenced by, you know, quite some time before, of your careless attending.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you become even more concerned about attending things wrongly later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you actually learn from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the time in itself, just clench your teeth, press the thumb against the roof of your mouth and endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, sometimes, just you need to, like a stronger man, pinch down the weaker man.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have a reflective contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is my responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, well, you just have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you endure it, once you haven't given in, you recognize, yeah, this is how it came about.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was through my careless attending.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so then you become more concerned about attending things carefully, which means such extreme examples where you just have to purely endure, will be arising less and less.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not... you're going away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like in the beginning, every thought of sensuality or anger is a wracking sensuality or wracking anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is just left or right, everywhere and nowhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you start developing that mind, once you start recognizing this, the influence of the, you know, the mountain streams in filling down the oceans, then you start... you stop all the time to empty the oceans, you just go and deal with the mountain streams, because you know eventually these oceans will dry up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense,
[SPEAKER_01]: But carefully attending to things beforehand, such extreme experiences won't be waiting for you down the line.
[SPEAKER_00]: But before you've done that... Before you've done that, you do need to endure a fair bit of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depending how quickly you do it as well, how quickly you extract yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to have that contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very negatively, to some extent, it will come down to endurance every now and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is a valid aspect of practice, endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what circumstances have brought the options for your choice in front of you, it will be you choosing to... well, you intentionally intending some aspects of it, even at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, it can be very painful to intend the opposite, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: to say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's only painful because your mind has been going in the direction of sensuality for such a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't been extracted from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't been attending properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, when you have to say no, it's just so hard because the whole avalanche is already going and it's so painful to stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you can always do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... That's what makes endurance easier.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can always say no to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have strength and wisdom in regard to... Like, you can have wisdom, you can know what you're supposed to choose, but if your mind is not developed, you will be swept by that avalanche of kind of predetermined directions that you've been cultivating for so long.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the wrong thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the wrong thing to do, but I can't help it, because I'm too weak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, you can say no to your weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can always be a step ahead.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how reflection works.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how intention works.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or step above.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have a family and 15 kids, and absolutely nothing stops you, that the next moment you just walk out and never come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or from your job, or from any other form of responsibility, that you yourself have accumulated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is the accumulation.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ocean is an accumulation of the water from the top.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you complain, but you are the one who left the tap open at the very top.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing stops you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, at any given time, you just go and close it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, just walk off.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what stops you is the weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, sometimes, people can do it over a period of time, when they have built up determination to leave, or determination to say no to whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, sometimes, something extreme needs to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like in the suttas, when people met with extreme misfortune, unthinkable misfortunes, and that snapped them out of it and made them go the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like the monks who haven't been quite fully developed in terms of arahantship, but they were there with the right view and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when they were about to die, when they were about to be set on fire by the by the highway robbers or whatever else, then they kind of abandoned it all internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: When when thing got real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the person... they're responsible for investing
[SPEAKER_00]: But nothing stops you to just walk out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing stops you to walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing stops you, to the next moment, to refuse to breathe.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, obviously, it's unpleasant to not breathe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you never even consider it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But breathing is another choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But something you keep doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing stops you to refuse to take a next in-breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And obviously, there's no point in not taking the next input, but I'm just illustrating the point I'm making.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say no at any given time to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the nature of the aggregate of choice, the aggregate of intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: You also...
[SPEAKER_01]: It has its own domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's separable from one, inconceivable from other aggregates, but in itself, it's an independent thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does intention suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intention is intended.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intention is... Feelings suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings... Feelings will be... Well, feelings will be... Feelings suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every feeling is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until you're innocent, where we're feeling nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings are suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you feel good or bad, pleasure or pain, or neutral, that's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you're susceptible to a feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, feelings, feel, intentions, intend, perceptions, perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, you can't possibly take these three and examine them without the two, the other two.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're always forgetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a degree of independence as a domain, perception and feeling and intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're inseparable, you're inconceivable without.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can't just think about feeling without involving perception and intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can discern them.
[SPEAKER_01]: As they arise simultaneously as this kind of group, like welded trio, you can still, within that, discern them, discern these separate elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus, intentions intend, feelings fuel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why does intention intend this, or intention intend that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, once you stop acting out of your feeling, once you fully understood the feelings, you wouldn't be intending based on how you feel, because that was inconceivable to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions cannot mix with feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a different domain, different aggregate.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're completely oblivious to each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions are intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: They intend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings are feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: They feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like intentions don't feel, nor feelings do intend.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's your ignorance, avidya, the attitude that kind of made the whole mess, whereby you end up intending based on how you felt, which was inconceivable to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until you knew that it was inconceivable, you were doing it for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then the question, why did I intend this or that, becomes, well, inconceivable as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why does intention intend?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's an intention that intends.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the question that you asked, why does this intend?
[SPEAKER_01]: That was only the intention that intended.
[SPEAKER_01]: It then tries to find a reason for intention elsewhere, in the feeling or whatever else, projected notion of the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can use, like this,
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea... well, I can use that desire for pleasure to lead me out, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can use the desire for pleasant... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting to be free from suffering is wanting to experience peace, which is a form of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to discern then what pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha did, you know, and he realized, okay, hold on, not all the pleasure is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of the pleasure is just pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not necessarily imply anything unwholesome, such as underlying tendency.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a pleasure of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, abandon all that pleasure to the one that's unwholesome, and then it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't ever... you won't have an issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then the pleasure that arises is the pleasure that's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the desire for pleasure can be used to basically develop wisdom to recognize that, sure, I could go after immediate pleasure, or relatively immediate pleasure, but that won't bring any kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they won't bring any freedom from desire for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will just maintain the same desire for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means I'll be just revolving on the server.
[SPEAKER_01]: And no matter how great the pleasure I get, the desire for pleasure remains intact.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means I'll need more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll need other pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll need different pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll need the same pleasure repetitively.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind will need pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what if...
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's actually unpleasant, being entrapped by constant pursuit of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to develop virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to... Because sometimes, sometimes I can't say no to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or sometimes, what I desire for my pleasure, I simply can't get.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I'll experience pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inevitably.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what if I abandon the whole thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: So that nothing can cause me pleasure or pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I won't be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, itself, that notion is very pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you forsake the immediate pleasure for the sake of that greater future pleasure of peace, of non-disturbance, of, you know, nibbāna, freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can also think about
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but looking into the future and saying, well, if I choose this now, not going after the last four objects, not indulging in lust, then, in the future, I'll be free from all sorts of... Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as simple as that, basically, like, reflecting, reflecting right here, right now, that if you choose to say no to the choice of lust, means, by not engaging in lust,
[SPEAKER_01]: Further down the line, in the future, you'll be able to seek the nature of that mass, and then be free from it once and for all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the restraint needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīla comes before the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: To get some full solutions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, because if you don't, if you don't, if you don't say no to it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, once you're in it, you can't be conceiving, okay, now, once I'm fully within the domain lust, I can practice a separation from lust, being free from lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you just place yourself in a position... Basically, again, the simile from the sutra is trying to light a fire with two sticks.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to dry them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have the two semi-dry sticks and you choose to stay on the ground and say no to the water, say no to lust, they will dry out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you need to do is resist the urge to go in the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is very oppressing at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you say no, you know that eventually these sticks will dry.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when they do dry, you can light the fire of knowledge and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: If, on the other hand, you have the semi-drastics and you choose to go back in the water, no matter how much you wish for them to be dry, you are in the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will not be dry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't have, then, any reasonable expectation to light up the fire of knowledge and see through the nature of lust, because you just set yourself back in the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reasoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Foreseeing it, expecting it, knowing where it's going to lead, then choosing the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why non-lust is... you kind of... you can never go wrong with it, by saying no to lust or greed, no to aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can never result in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Renunciation can never result in unwholesome, which is why it is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can never partake in anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're ever in doubt, oh, should I just say yes or no, just see which one has the lust in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which choice will have lust?
[SPEAKER_01]: If saying no implies lust, then do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, if I stay here, where, you know, I'll be subjected to lustful impressions or to anger impressions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: If I stay here, I leave myself susceptible to these things, so I'll go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I won't say yes to staying here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if somebody says, do you wanna... do you wanna... do you wanna go elsewhere?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that that place is more risky in terms of inducing lust or aversion or whatever, then you say no to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you always say no to lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in worldly terms, that might sometimes mean saying yes to certain things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I want to leave this place.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I don't want to stay here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, no, I want to go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I want to stay here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that choice, if there's reason, will be determined, like, which one is based... which one implies non-lust, or which one implies cessation of lust, cessation of aversion, cessation of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's not that clear, but then you see, well, which one is more likely?
[SPEAKER_01]: To be implying non-lust, non-aversion, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what you choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even like, oh, okay, oops, I went to this place and now it's filled with... Oops, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, within that, you can choose the non-lust, non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean giving in further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you intended, firstly, to go against the lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the main... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever the external results come.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your choice was governed by the... by the kind of... well, the criteria of renunciation in terms of greed, aversion, del
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, I end up in the middle of the village, but I came there through avoiding the other lust, and now here I keep doing the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's always a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, lust, aversion, delusion can never be thrown on you without your choice or say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not be able to say no to it if you're not developed in regard to it, but it always remains down to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the standard.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like the first angle to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the standard that you'd start or the base.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do my best to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can take that further, even to your own thinking, whereby you might not be doing anything unwholesome in terms of the body of the speech, but your mind not necessarily always thinks good stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you take it there, and then address that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sometimes they ask, well, I want to go for a retreat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you give me a brief instruction so that, yeah, I can ponder on it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you know, it's a wholesome abandonment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you know, it's a wholesome cultivating.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Three months later, arahant emerges from that retreat, because that's all they contemplate, and that's enough to contemplate.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like that, because it sets up a person that... What is unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is wholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then it sets up you, that whole contemplation, having to watch your choices, having to watch your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this worth it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That line?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, is this a good choice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this wholesome choice or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, have a look.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it founded in your desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In what desire is it founded?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I want to go and live on top of the mountain, where it's quiet, undisturbed, solitude, so I can practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a desire that I can tell it has a good chance of resulting in freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some other person...
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to... Externally, it can look the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to go and live on top of the mountain, free from people, free from disturbance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I hate them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't live with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't stand them.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't listen to other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are a source of my anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, out of that anger, I want to run there where I'll be protected.
[SPEAKER_01]: from the disturbances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not necessarily...
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to run the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I can't deal with this anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want to run through the game where I will address that anger, so that I can never ever be angry in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you see it, you'll respond.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, basically, this is what bothers me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just shut it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how you shut it?
[SPEAKER_01]: I shut it by going to a different monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that monastery starts bothering me, I go to another monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I live on top of the hill where nobody will disturb me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I, myself, won't be doing anything about the possibility to be disturbed in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is not that you've been disturbed through anger or lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that you lie about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if anger and lust never ever arise in the future, if you... if you're actually... if it remains as a possibility, it means you're still within the domain of anger and lust, which means there's no question... no... no idea, like, notion of freedom there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the real one, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what you recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about me suffering right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about possibility to suffer in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that suffering in itself, that concern, is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you undo that, then you can't suffer in the present, by anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you cease to be liable to aversion, liable to lust, liable to delusion, even if you're in the middle of the village, nobody can make you angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody can make you lustful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, sometimes you need to extract yourself out from it, but you have to be clear as to why are you doing so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether your desire is rooted in genuine desire to be free from suffering down the line, or if it's rooted in simple desire to run away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this bothers me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll go when things are more pleasant and peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you know, you won't be in control in the new situation, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that changes...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you have people who live, like, I don't know, I don't know, 20, 30 years, and if they ever end up back in the community or in a hospital with other people, they just lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no involvement, no development, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you have the other people,
[SPEAKER_01]: You might have seen a degree of this, but then, they develop a view on account of it, which overrides, like, the current experience, because that's how... that's why views are dangerous, because it can contradict exactly what you're experiencing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they might... they're developing a view that, no, you should never leave the group of people, because they will be only running away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be running away, if that's what you act out of.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you act out of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm gonna run away from this right now, so that I can deal with it fully, so that then I wouldn't care whether I'm alone or with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's a good running away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people who kind of might have seen the danger in running away, or met a few people who ran away, then they came back and lost it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, without trying it themselves, without distinguishing the... the... the... like the nature of the motive in itself, they end up developing the view that, no, leaving the group, leaving the... the... the setting is bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You make it good or bad depending on, like, the reasons for your action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depending whether it was rooted in wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the view is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you just override any good and bad by saying it's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it can be good or can be bad depending on why you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like leaving the group.
[SPEAKER_01]: Going to live alone, or similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you put a blanket rule over it, then, okay, well, you just cover it, then that's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you've covered it all up, and now you can't see the nature of it, which means there won't be any discernment of wholesome, un... rooted in wholesome, rooted in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You decided it beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, both those things are... the externals... it's because of the external things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, therefore, I'll stay in a community because... To keep the external things in the same way so I won't suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because being in it, there's many people that helps.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not incidental that always those views that are kind of pasted over the actual particular things that you might be experiencing, those views are always fueled by the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're not taking responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, I will condemn everybody that leaves the group.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because deep down inside, I'm terrified to do it myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I will condemn the group.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because deep down inside, I'm incapable of living without people.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just find it intolerable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, people end up adopting their views based on the underlying kind of notions that are unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either fear, or hate, or lust, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like, oh, I will not leave, go and live on top of the mountain, I'll stay in the monastery, because the community is good, it's good to help people, it's good... And deep down inside, I'm simply afraid to go without food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it can be as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm afraid that my food will be too rough on the mountain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll find every single justification to stay in the monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Including meeting people, distractions, engagements, duties, sense of importance, sense of accomplishment, sense of courteousness, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, I met quite a fair deal of other people who know being a monk is about living alone in the forest and doing this and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they have such serious issues that they can't stand anywhere, no matter how kind and good they are to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just pure hatred towards another.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way for me to remain in this kind of setting that I've sort of ended up in, is to run away from everybody and hide in the forest and just keep it to a bare minimum meeting with others, because I just can't stand them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't know how to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just lose my composure every single time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, externally, you can paint either of those unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha said you live in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he said something else in conjunction to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said only those who are ready to live in the forest should live in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said you should keep in the community.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah, he said only those who are kind of capable of keeping in the community should keep in the community.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he did not adopt a rule that kind of overrides everything else, regardless of the actual particular circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why he wouldn't have made all those dhūtangas mandatory.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when Devadatta Nagarjuna has requested that, you know, rāyagraha should be mandatory, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: If one thought should be mandatory.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let those who want to wear rāyagraha, wear rāyagraha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let those who don't want to do it, don't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whether they want to do it or not want to do it, should be determined, well, through their understanding of wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the person who understood wholesome is unwholesome, will want wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And being an ascetic is not necessarily wholesome for everyone, because people can do it for very wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can refine that, exactly that thing, to the extent whereby you have inspiration to go out of the monastery and live in the mountains.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not necessarily coming out of unwholesome, but it's coming out of, well, intoxication that came with inspiration.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, well, there might be a great deal of delusion involved in this, because I'm not acting out of genuine recognition that this would be good for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm acting because I'm so inspired and full of energy to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you take it cautiously.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you go halfway up the mountain, so to speak, and see if that's what... if that's... if that's bringing wholesome to increase, unwholesome to decrease, or other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's other way around, we'll go back, restart it another time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But also, it... it clears up the question... when you have the question, what should I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't do those.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm intending.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever I do,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not bad to have sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not bad to have a wife.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not bad to have kids.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends on what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: People think in terms of the eternal judgment.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is bad, this is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends on what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Killing is always bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lying is... breaking five precepts is always bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's the five... it's the basic requirement that distinguishes humans from animals, if they stick to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But everything else, further on, well, that's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not judging people who have families and don't want to leave it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just saying that if this is what you want to do, well, that contradicts it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't have it both ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be saying, I'm a genuine practitioner of the Buddha's teaching and at the same time be engaging in sexual intercourse, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the Buddha said himself, you can't have it open.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's exactly the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like, you recognize, for yourself, whether the things you want to do, your choices, your intentions, even the way you attend to things, are being rooted in lust, aversion and delusion, or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But something was... Externally, you... that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there is a basis of the five precepts or the eight precepts later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, everything else in between can be, you know, very good and very bad externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But internally, actually, you are the only one they would know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good to go...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good to sit on a group retreat or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But someone says like, yeah, I want to be...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to give up craving for another person.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to give up craving for sexual activity, but I'm just not ready for that right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you chose to not be ready.
[SPEAKER_01]: You chose that to be the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes, you know, things...
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it depends on what you attend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, things can get very subtle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not necessarily bad, or rather, it's not necessarily unwholesome, but it can be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say you are hungry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need the food in order to not die.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at the same time, you choose only the food that you like.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're clearly, basically, acting out of lust for taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of also implies eating the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why you should, like, attend carefully.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the contemplation that we chant in the morning back in the monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the reasons why you eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, okay, there's no question, you abstain from sex, you abstain from killing, you abstain from lying, but you can't abstain from eating, because you'll die.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can say, well, I will eat only things I don't like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's not... that's again putting on an external decision.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you do only what you don't like, then you might start liking torturing yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might start enjoying that unwholesomely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, there won't be any wisdom arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just want to make sure that while you're eating, you make sure that you're active eating,
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't get rooted in unwholesome desire for the pleasant taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you won't be running away from nice food that you like, that you liked.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you won't be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people think, oh, I really want to eat dish A on account of dish B, which I don't really like, so I should really go with what I don't like.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's just like projecting it externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, putting responsibility on that which you don't like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying, I will choose what I don't like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, you can do it once or twice, but sooner or later, you will get dependent on the view to always do the opposite of what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: you will become dependent on the view to torture yourself, to cause, to intentionally inflict pain to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sooner or later, you can't sustain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you want to do, basically, is recognize, I have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether I eat dish A or B, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: I prefer dish A to dish B. I might eat both, and then remain mindful in terms of the dish B, to not be hating and thinking about dish A, while I'm eating dish B, and at the same time, while I'm eating dish A, to not be like, well, overjoyed on account of it, or careless in regard to the experience of taste of the dish A.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you remain mindful in regard to both tastes, because you have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, above all, you remain mindful as to why you have to eat, in order to sustain the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that thought, literally, if that thought remains established in you, you will not overdo the joy when it comes to the dish you like, nor will you be too concerned when it comes to the dish you don't like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the point is to eat whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you remain rooted in that, through your mindfulness, means there won't be any prize given to the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You carelessly attend to what you're eating, you forget why you're eating, or rather you forget to root things in the right reasons for eating, you will inevitably be taken by what?
[SPEAKER_01]: By the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be taken by that which is the strongest, which is the pool of the taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the same act of eating can be rūcā and kundalini, and you're responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to... and when you start looting yourself properly and establish from there, then you wouldn't care.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, like I have disciples who live only on one handful of rice every second day.
[SPEAKER_01]: While at that time, I would be eating like the finest curries, and I would sometimes eat a bowl full to the brim.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he would eat two alms bowls to the brim of the nicest food, while he has disciples who live on a handful of rice.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that was the goal of practice, to live on... they would not be respecting him any... in any way whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not... the goal of the practice is to not be affected by the food, to not be affected by the senses, to not be turned...
[SPEAKER_01]: To not being made rooted in unwholesome based on the pull of the senses, that's the goal of the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's a pleasant taste, touch, sounds, so on, it will not pull you into unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the goal of the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you establish that, then you can eat whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you establish the principle and then you're not pulled.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, the Buddha can have the finest silk robes and three bowls of food in front of him, if he wants, and you'll still respect him as much as you did on the first day, when he was just living as an ascetic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, when he's kind of frequented by the kings and everything, you'll respect him.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know where the goal is, and you understood what he's teaching was.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that teaching frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might choose to live under a root of tree, enjoying one handful of rice every three days, because you don't need more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what makes you happy and content, and not disturbed and peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you'll still respect him while he lives in a palace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that was never the point of the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the external.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Epictetus says it's very similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing about food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being at a banquet and then...
[SPEAKER_00]: Food comes your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just take, you know, what you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't like to call, grab, eat more than you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you happen to come across that luxurious food comes, happens to be... You have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have it because you need to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's really low food, just like... And if you're like, oh, should I, should I, should I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just re-establish the mindfulness into why you need to eat and keep that thought while you're eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as that door is present, while you're eating, no matter to what degree it's present, sometimes more, sometimes less, if you're establishing it mindfully, as an anchor, you'll be eating for the right reasons, no matter what.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, you know, I remember I met people, monks, who always, you know, a big dhāna, loads of food, like, I don't know, 50 dishes, and then, instead of taking responsibility for the fact that you have to eat,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then eating what, you know, you find agreeable, not necessarily always what you really, really like, but say, you know, I don't like certain things, but I'll take them, because I learned that they are very nutritional, that they can keep me going further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I will have to eat less.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go for that, even if you don't like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes I find out that this really thing that I really happen to like, I really, I love the taste of that, it's also very, very good for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll take that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, I will not forget why I need to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, those monks would not necessarily think like... well, they would not descend to that level, so they would recognize the problem of preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of preference is not a problem, but preference-inducing lust is a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead of recognizing, taking up responsibility for it, they try to deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they would either always take what they don't like,
[SPEAKER_01]: I always take what I want less.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means, okay, so you're basically attributing choice to the view of going after that which is less desirable.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am not responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are three choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll go for the one I least want.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's already something you've chosen beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you're attributing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then I even met some monks who were like saying, I will take only every third dish, whatever that dish might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, so now you're attributing responsibility to the chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, all of that is irrelevant, actually, if they were to remain mindful as to why they're eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: But clearly, the failure of putting on importance of how the dishes are chosen, means they're not mindful when they were eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, hey, I didn't choose out of my preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've chosen out of this every-third-dish algorithm that I wrote.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I can forget about it, because now it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever I have in my bowl, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of it is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you should start.
[SPEAKER_01]: No food is fine to eat, good or bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: You only have to eat because you want to survive.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you keep that, then you wouldn't care what food is in your bowl, whether it's tasty or not, because you realize none of it is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they all come from the point of view that food is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: If in some way there's a bigger problem than the other, then you try to avoid by choosing the opposite, da-da-da-da-da.
[SPEAKER_01]: Point being, none of that would actually be a problem for them, if they were to remain mindful while they're eating, as to why.
[SPEAKER_01]: While they're eating, as to why they're eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hungry, full stomach.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's impossible to eat without giving in to the
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a sense domain of taste to the animal that pertains to that domain, to that pool.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what I can do is keep it in check.
[SPEAKER_01]: I let it eat, because it needs to eat, but I'll keep it in check as to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll ground it, I'll train it to the reason why I'm eating, which is to sustain this body no more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on some days, there will be food that that animal likes, that the sense of taste
[SPEAKER_01]: Finds it agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Defines it disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you won't be bothered by going through all this effort of always finding a disagreeable taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize, agreeable or disagreeable, both are in the same domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that I was affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can be equally affected by disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sometimes, if you don't... Like, if you always go around choosing the disagreeable taste, sometimes you're presented by tastes and none of them is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you going to choose then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you won't be able to not be affected by agreeable taste, because you were running away from it into disagreeable, which was also on the level of taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't care about agreeable taste or disagreeable taste, you care about the nature of taste affecting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that can be undone, or that can be accomplished, not being affected by that, can be accomplished simply by remaining mindful as to why do you need... why you need to give in to the taste in the first place, be it agreeable, disagreeable or mutual.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you keep mind... when you develop enough mindfulness in regard to that, then you wouldn't care what you're eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't care what you're choosing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't care how you're choosing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't care if somebody else puts the food in your bowl, or if you go and put the food in your bowl.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't care if you're just going to choose the agreeable stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not affected by agreeable, none more than you're affected by disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're beyond both.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you won't be overeating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of indulgence, you won't be... Under-eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Under-eating